A Finding Aid to the George Leslie Stout papers, 1855, 1897-1978, in the Archives of American Art AAA.stougeor
Archives of American Art
- Correspondence, 1922-1978; Series 2; 2.5 Linear feet Box 1-3, OV 8
  - Professional, 1925-1978; 2.4
    - State Department, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Timken Art Gallery, 1971-1978 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - University of Pittsburgh, 1925; 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Winterthur Museum, 1972-1978 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Worcester Art Museum, 1947-1978 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Oversized Maps of Hillstead in Farmington, Connecticut, 1961-1972 (Box OV 8, Folder 2)
      Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 7.
  - Miscellaneous, 1923-1978; 2.5
    The letters are arranged alphabetically with the unidentified correspondents grouped together in one folder at the end.
    Miscellaneous correspondence is from individuals with three letters or less and unidentified people or whose names were illegible.
    - A-D Miscellaneous, bulk 1969-1978; 1923-1978 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - F-J Miscellaneous, 1954-1978; 1926 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - K-N Miscellaneous, 1971-1978; 1939-1948 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - P, R-U, W Miscellaneous, 1947-1978 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Unidentified Correspondents, circa 1944-1977 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Writings, 1927-1978; Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet Box 3-4
  Writings by Stout include typescript drafts and published articles, speeches, notes, and one folder of images and captions for his book The Care of Pictures. All of the writings are by Stout except for three papers about art conservation written by others.
  This series is arranged as 3 subseries:
  3.1: Typescript Drafts, 1927-1978
  3.2: Publications, 1941-1969
  3.3: Notes and Writings By Others, 1948, 1962-1974
  The three papers written by others are grouped together in one folder at the end of the series.
  - Typescript Drafts, 1927-1978; 3.1
    - "Andokides", 1927 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - "Callot's Landscape", 1927 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - "Buffalmacco and the Badia Frescoes", 1927-1928 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - "Giotto's Maxims of Composition", circa 1930-1978 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - "Art for Your Sake", circa 1930-1978 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - "Art and Opportunity", circa 1930-1978 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - "The State of Knowledge in the Arts", circa 1930-1978 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - "An Observation on Italian Painting Method in the Fifteenth Century", 1936-1947 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Worcester Art Museum Graduation Speech, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - "The Professional Artist", 1948 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - "Reattachment of Loose Paint", 1950 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - "Windows", 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - "Comments on Laminal Disruption", 1955-1960 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Edward W. Forbes Memorial Service, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - "Portland Survey", 1973-1978 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - "Trial Outline of Conservation in the Arts", 1973 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Coremans Memorial, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Rutherford John Gettens Memorial, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - "Description of Film Cracks", 1974 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - "Provisional Conspectus of Conservation in the Arts", 1975 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - "Changes in Attitude Towards Conservation in the Arts", 1975 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - "Early Years of Conservation at the Fogg Art Museum", 1977 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Editorial for Studies in Conservation, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Publications, 1941-1969; 3.2
    Publications contain Stout's articles on art conservation in journals and magazines.
    - "The Study of Art", 1941 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - "The Need for Objective Examination", 1948 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - "Long-Range Conservation", 1949 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - "The Viewpoint of the Conservator", 1950 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - "A Monument of Byzantine Wall Painting - The Method of Construction", 1958 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - "Thirty Years of Conservation in the Arts", 1964 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - "A Roman Mosaic Pavement Rebuilt", 1969 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Studies in Conservation, Volume 14, number 4, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Notes, 1962-1974; 1948; 3.3
    This subseries includes images and captions for The Care of Pictures, miscellaneous notes, drafts for the text on holiday cards, and bibliographical notes for a later edition of Stout's book. Also found here are art conservation papers written by others.
    - The Care of Pictures Images and Captions, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Bibliographical Notes for Dover Edition of The Care of Pictures, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Holiday Card Drafts, circa 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Art Conservation Papers Written by Others, 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Subject Files, 1918; 1943-1978; Series 4; 1 Linear feet Box 4, OV 8-9
  Subject files concern Stout's work as consultant and his affliations with and memberships in various organizations after his retirement.
  This series is arranged as 2 subseries:
  4.1: Consultations, circa 1955-1958, 1971-1978
  4.2: Institutions, 1971-1978
  - Consultations, 1970-1978; circa 1955-1958; 4.1
    Stout worked as a consultant on conservation projects with museums, universities, and arts organizations. Consultations folders include photographs, reports, floor plans and other miscellaneous materials.
    - Foothill Electronics Museum, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Minneapolis Museum, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Condition Reports, 1972; 1966 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Mosque of Kariye Camii, Istanbul, circa 1955 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Oversized material in OV 9, Folder 1.
    - Mt. Athos, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Oversized material housed in OV 9, Folder 2.
    - San Francisco, 1970-1977 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - San Simeon Floor Plans, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Oversized material housed in OV 8, Folder 3.
    - San Simeon Surveys, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - San Simeon X-Ray Room and Conservation Workroom, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Oversized material housed in OV 9, Folder 3.
    - San Simeon Historical Monument, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 15-16)
    - San Simeon Historical Monument, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - San Simeon Miscellaneous, circa 1972 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Timken Art Gallery, 1974; 1978; 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Woodside Village Church, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Oversized San Simeon Floor Plans, 1971 (Box OV 8, Folder 3)
      Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 12.
    - Oversized News Clippings, 1955 (Box OV 9, Folder 1)
      Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 9.
    - Oversized News Clippings, 1970-1972 (Box OV 9, Folder 2)
      Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 10.
    - Oversized San Simeon X-Ray Room Ground Plans, 1972 (Box OV 9, Folder 3)
      Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 14.
  - Institutions, 1971-1978; 4.2
    Found here are papers documenting Stout's affiliations with art and conservation organizations, councils, and advisory boards. All date after his retirement as the director of the Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum in 1970. Documents include meeting minutes, newsletters, photographs, and other assorted materials.
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - American Association of Museums, 1971-1978 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - American Institute for Conservation Incorporation and By-Laws, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - American Institute for Conservation Newsletters and Minutes, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Anderson Collection, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Association of Art Museum Directors, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Bay Area Art Conservation Guild, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - College Art Association, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - International Council of Museums, 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - International Institute for Conservation, 1971-1977 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Lone Mountain College, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Mansoor Collection, 1972; 1975 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      Oversized material housed in OV 9, Folder 4.
    - National Conservation Advisory Council, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - National Endowment for the Arts, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Radiation Detection Company, circa 1971 (Box 4, Folder 35)
      Oversized material housed in OV 8, Folder 4.
    - Radiation Safety Certificate, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - San Francisco Bay Area Cooperative, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Western Association of Art Conservators, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Western Regional Conference, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Oversized Charts about Radioactivity, circa 1971 (Box OV 8, Folder 4)
      Oversized items from Box 4, Folder 35.
    - Oversized News Clipping, 1975 (Box OV 9, Folder 4)
      Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 32.
- Monuments, Fine Arts & Archives Section Files, 1942-1955; 1972-1975; 1918; Series 5; 0.5 Linear feet Box 5
  This series is comprised of Stout's military records from his service during and immediately after World War II in the Monuments, Fine Arts, and Archives section of the U.S. Army. The records include certificates, army directives, appointments, forms, reports, and a few scattered photographs.
  This series is arranged as three subseries.
  5.1: Military Records, 1918, 1943-1955
  5.2: Monuments Men Publications, 1942-circa 1950, 1972-1975
  5.3: Photographs, circa 1945
  - Military Records, 1918; 1943-1955; 5.1
    These records include certificates, army directives, appointments, forms, reports, and a few official photographs. There is also a certificate of Stout's honorable discharge from World War I and documentation of his Bronze Star award.
    The records are arranged chronologically to reflect the original order of the documents.
    - Honorable Discharge Certificate, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Original certificate and photocopies.
    - Military Records, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Includes small black and white photographs of George Leslie Stout.
    - Military Records, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Military Records, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Bronze Star Medal, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Military Records, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Military Records, 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Records on the Exhibition of Paintings from the Kaiser Friedrich Museum, Berlin, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Military Reports, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Military Records, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Military Records, 1951-1955 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Undated Military Records, 1943-1950 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Monuments Men Publications, 1972-1975; 1942-circa 1950; 5.2
    The printed materials in this subseries largely consist of articles and journals written and signed by several Monuments Men and inscribed to George Stout. Many of the articles are about experiences in the Monuments, Fine Arts & Archives (MFAA) Section. There are articles written by Langdon Warner, Lincoln Kirstein, Theodore Sizer, and several others. Some of the papers describe MFAA activities but are not written by Monuments Men. A few records are in French and Japanese.
    - Langdon Warner's Commencement Address, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      The commencement address is inscribed by Langdon Warner to George Leslie Stout.
    - College Art Journal, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Journal includes articles by Walker Hancock, Marvin C. Ross, and Andrew C. Ritchie about their experiences as Monuments Men.
    - "Some Inside Information Around the 'Forged' Vermeer of Rotterdam", 1946 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - A Walpolean at War, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      This booklet was written by Theodore Sizer with an inscription to George Stout.
    - La Protection Scientifique des Ouevres d'Art en Temps de Guerre, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      This booklet was written by Paul Coremans with an inscription to George Leslie Stout.
    - "Arts and Monuments", circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      This article was written by Lincoln Kirstein.
    - Aperture, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      This book contains an article written by Lincoln Kirstein and the cover is inscribed by Kirstein to George Stout.
    - Fourth Presentation of the Charles Lang Freer Medal, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      This booklet was published by the Freer Gallery of Art for the presentation of the Charles Lang Freer Medal to Tanaka Ichimatsu who assisted with art conservation in Japan after World War II. The booklet is inscribed to George Stout by Ichimatsu.
    - Mr. Stinson's 'Pet City' - The Sparing of Kyoto, 1945, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      Booklet researching the reason Kyoto was spared as a target for the nuclear bomb. The booklet is inscribed by author Otis Cary, a World War II veteran, to George Stout.
  - Photographs, circa 1945; 5.3
    There are 2 folders of photographs about the Monuments, Fine Arts & Archives section. One folder contains a few photographs, several of them duplicates, depicting groups of unidentifed soldiers on a ship. Stout is only in two of the images including a group photograph with Lamont Moore, Walker Hancock and other Monuments Men. There are also negatives of 12 images, four of which have been developed into black and white photographs, that show La Gleize Church and the town of Ambleve, Belgium during 1945, probably soon after the Battle of the Bulge.
    - La Gleize Church and Ambleve, Belgium, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1945 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Personal Business Records, 1938-1978; Series 6; 0.1 Linear feet Box 5, 7 folders
  The records in this subseries are assorted legal and financial papers, such as Stout's will and estate documents, receipts, travel expenses, and donations.
  - George Leslie Stout's Will, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Estate and Property Papers, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Power of Attorney Papers, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Copyright Claim, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Court Case Over Johnson Estate Exhibition Paintings, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Receipts and Travel Expenses, 1972-1978 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Signed Deed of Gift Agreeing to Donation of Conservation Roundtable Tape Recordings to FAIC, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Printed Materials, 1926-1977; Series 7; 0.8 Linear feet Box 5-6, OV 9
  Printed materials include news clippings, bulletins, brochures, conference papers, press releases and magazines.
  - News Clippings, 1930-1947; 1930 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    Oversized material housed in OV 9, Folder 5.
  - News Clippings, 1962-1972 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    Oversized material housed in OV 9, Folder 6.
  - News Clippings, 1950-1954 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - News Clippings, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    Oversized material housed in OV 9, Folder 7.
  - News Clippings, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    Oversized material housed in OV 9, Folder 8.
  - News Clippings, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    Oversized material housed in OV 9, Folder 9.
  - News Clippings, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Undated News Clippings, 1945-1977 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Magazine and Journal Articles, 1926-1948; 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Magazine and Journal Articles, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Magazine and Journal Articles, 1974-1977 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Undated Magazine and Journal Articles, circa 1945-circa 1965 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Grace Cathedral, San Francisco, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Oriental Art Auction Catalog, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Studies in the History of Art, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    Inscribed to George Stout from Richard Buck.
  - New York State Award 1974 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Bronze Disease and its Treatment, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Brochures, 1945-1951; 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Undated Brochures, circa 1950-1977 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Memorial Tributes for Friends and Colleagues, 1962-1975 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Museum Bulletins, 1973-1976; 1936-1947 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Museum Reports, 1963-1974 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Newsletters & Announcements, circa 1971-1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Press Releases, 1954; 1971-1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Review of The Care of Pictures, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1959-1977 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Oversized News Clippings, circa 1947 (Box OV 9, Folder 5)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 31.
  - Oversized News Clippings, 1969-1972 (Box OV 9, Folder 6)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 32.
  - Oversized News Clippings, 1973-1975 (Box OV 9, Folder 7)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 34.
  - Oversized News Clippings, 1975 (Box OV 9, Folder 8)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 35.
  - Oversized News Clippings, 1976 (Box OV 9, Folder 9)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 36.
- Artwork & Sketchbooks, 1970-1977; circa 1924-circa 1938; Series 8; 0.1 Linear feet Box 6
  Artwork consists of numerous sketches and one sketchbook by George Leslie Stout. The sketchbook is filled with figure drawings. Sketches are in pencil and ink of landscapes, animals, people and scenes from travels. Stout loosely grouped the sketches together by topic with titles such as "Pool Doodles" of people lounging by a poolside and "Pencil Studies Zoo, Park Studies," which are sketches of animals and landscapes. Stout also made holiday greetings cards for which he drew illustrations and added text. Photocopies of several of the completed greeting cards are included. There is one caricature of Eric Brown, Director of the National Gallery of Canada, by Murray Pease, Stout's friend and colleague.
  - Figure Drawing Sketchbook, circa 1924 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Sketchbook of figure drawings of models.
  - Sketches, circa 1938 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Sketches of men playing baseball and three drawings of landscapes, 2 of unidentified locations and one of Oliver's Island, Thames in England dated 1938.
  - Copies of Greeting Card Designs, circa 1972-1976 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "Pool Doodles" Sketches, circa 1970 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Several sketches of people lounging by a pool, location not specified. Sketches were grouped together by Stout along with the label "Pool Doodles."
  - Desert Sketches, circa 1970 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Sketches grouped together in a folder with an insert labelled "desert." Drawings depict objects such animal skulls and pieces of driftwood. There are two landscapes of an unidentified location.
  - Hilandar Monastery on Mt. Athos, Greece Sketches, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Pencil drawings of Hilandar Monastery on Mount Athos in Greece dated August, 1971. Drawings are probably from a trip Stout took to the location. The images depict the interior and exterior of the monastery as well as the surrounding landscape. Many drawings have annotations such as "from the window of Room No. 3, Monastery of Hilandari. August 1971."
  - Park and Zoo Sketches, 1977; 1975 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    These drawings were grouped together by Stout along with the label "Pencil Studies Zoo, Park Studies." These include a few ink drawings of people, trees, and park scenes which Stout drew at Balboa Park in California. There are also some pencil sketches of Scandavian reindeer and Uganda Kob which he drew at the zoo.
  - Caricature of Eric Brown by Murray Pease, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Photographs and Negatives, 1897-1978; circa 1855; Series 9; 0.2 Linear feet Box 6-7
  This series includes photographs, negatives, contact prints, and a few slides of Stout, his friends and colleagues, travels, and events such as arts conservation conferences and receptions.
  - Micajah and Abraham Lincoln Stout, circa 1855 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Childhood Photos, circa 1897 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Self-Portraits, 1922 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Fogg Art Museum Class, 1928-1929 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - International Congress of the History of Art, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Conservation Personnel, 1930-1935 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Friends and Acquaintances, circa 1940; circa 1972 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - George Stout Informal and Group Photographs, circa 1945-1974 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Lisbon Reception, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Portraits of George Leslie Stout, circa 1965-1977 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Sharon Green, 1972; 1970 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Palo Alto, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - San Simeon, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Live Oaks, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Mexico Trip, circa 1975 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Reno, Nevada, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - A. R. Stout, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Conservation Projects for Paintings, circa 1977 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1971 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Unidentified Individuals, 1897-1978 (Box 7, Folder 11)